These dragons from deep time are incredible creatures.
هذه التنانين من العصور السحيقة مخلوقات مٌذهلة
They're bizzarre,
وغريبة أيضًا
they're beautiful,
وجميلة كذلك،
and there's very little we know about them.
ما نعرفه عنها يعتبر قليلًا جدًا.
These thoughts were going through my head
كانت تلك الأفكار تدور في رأسي
when I looked at the pages of my first dinosaur book.
حينما شاهدت ديناصورات للمرة الأولى في كتاب.
I was about five years old at the time,
كنت حينها في حوالي الخامسة من عمري،
and I decided there and then
وقررت في تلك اللحظة
that I would become a paleontologist.
أنني سأُصبح عالم مستحاثات.
Paleontology allowed me to combine my love for animals
علم المستحاثات مكنني من دمج حبي للحيوانات
with my desire to travel to far-flung corners of the world.
مع رغبتي للسفر إلى أقصى بقاع العالم.
And now, a few years later, I've led several expeditions
والآن، وبعد مرور بضع سنوات، قمت بعدد من الرحلات الاستكشافية
to the ultimate far-flung corner on this planet, the Sahara.
إلى أبعد البقاع من هذه الأرض، إلى الصحراء.
I've worked in the Sahara because I've been on a quest
عملت في الصحراء لأنني كنت في مسعى
to uncover new remains of a bizarre, giant predatory dinosaur
للكشف عن بقايا جديدة لديناصور غريب، مفترس وعملاق
called Spinosaurus.
يدعى سبينوصور.
A few bones of this animal have been found
عُثر على بعض العظام لهذا المخلوق
in the deserts of Egypt
في صحراء مصر
and were described about 100 years ago by a German paleontologist.
كان قد وصفها عالم مستحاثات ألماني قبل 100 سنة تقريبا.
Unfortunately, all his Spinosaurus bones were destroyed in World War II.
ولسوء الحظ، كل العظام للسبينوصور قد تهشمت في الحرب العالمية الثانية.
So all we're left with are just a few drawings and notes.
وكان ما بقي لنا مجرد رسومات وبعض الملاحظات.
From these drawings,
من تلك الرسومات،
we know that this creature, which lived about 100 million years ago,
قد تبين أن ذلك المخلوق قد عاش منذ حوالي 100 مليون سنة،
was very big,
وكان كبير الحجم،
it had tall spines on its back, forming a magnificent sail,
كان العمود الفقري على ظهره طويلا، ويُشكل شراعا مذهل،
with conical teeth,
ذو أسنان مخروطية،
that may have been used to catch slippery prey, like fish.
يمكن أن يكون قد استخدمها للقبض على فريسة زلقة، مثل الأسماك.
But that was pretty much all we knew
هذا جُل ما عرفناه
about this animal for the next 100 years.
عن هذا المخلوق على مدى الـ100 سنة المقبلة.
My fieldwork took me to the border region between Morocco and Algeria,
أخذني عملي الميداني إلى الحدود بين المغرب والجزائر
a place called the Kem Kem.
في مكان يدعى "كِم كِم."
It's a difficult place to work in.
مكان ذو بيئة صعبة للعمل فيه
You have to deal with sandstorms and snakes and scorpions,
يجب عليك أن تتعامل مع العواصف الرملية والثعابين والعقارب،
and it's very difficult to find good fossils there.
ومن الصعب جدًا العثور على أحافير في ذلك المكان.
But our hard work paid off.
ولكن مجهودنا الشاق آتى ثماره.
We discovered many incredible specimens.
فقد عثرنا على العديد من العينات المدهشة
that had ever been found in this part of the Sahara.
يمكن العثور عليه في تلك البقعة من الصحراء.
We found remains of giant predatory dinosaurs,
وجدنا مجددًا بقايا ديناصور عملاق مفترس
medium-sized predatory dinosaurs,
من الديناصورات المفترسة متوسطة الحجم
and seven or eight different kinds of crocodile-like hunters.
وما بين سبعة أو ثمانية أنواع مختلفة ما يشبه التماسيح الصيادة.
These fossils were deposited in a river system.
ترسبت هذه الحفريات في نظام نهري.
The river system was also home to a giant, car-sized coelacanth,
كان النظام النهري موطنًا لأسماك الكُهُوفِ الشَوكيةِ العملاقة
and the skies over the river system were filled with pterosaurs,
كانت سماء النظام النهري مغطاة بالتيروصورات،
flying reptiles.
الزواحف الطائرة.
It was a pretty dangerous place,
كان المكان خطير جدًا،
not the kind of place where you'd want to travel to if you had a time machine.
ليس من نوعية الأمكنة التي تتمنى زيارتها إذا كنت تملك آلة زمن
So we're finding all these incredible fossils of animals
قد تمكنا من العثور على مستحاثات لتلك المخلوقات المذهلة
that lived alongside Spinosaurus,
قد عاشت بجانب السبينوصور،
but Spinosaurus itself proved to be very elusive.
ولكن السبينوصور نفسه كان بعيد المنال
We were just finding bits and pieces
فقد عثرنا فقط على أجزاء وقطع
and I was hoping that we'd find a partial skeleton at some point.
وكنت على أمل أن أعثر على جزء من هيكله العظمي في مرحلة ما.
Finally, very recently,
أخيرًا، وفي وقت قريب جدًا،
we were able to track down a dig site
استطعنا تعقب موقع للحفر
where a local fossil hunter found several bones of Spinosaurus.
حيث وجد صياد أحفوري محلي عدة عظام للسبينوصور.
We returned to the site, we collected more bones.
عدنا إلى ذلك الموقع، وجمعنا العديد من العظام
of this bizarre creature.
لذلك المخلوق المميز.
And we were able to reconstruct it.
وتمكنا من إعادة بنائه.
We now know that Spinosaurus had a head
نحن نعرف الآن أن سبينوصور كان له رأس
a little bit like a crocodile,
أشبه ما يكون برأس التمساح،
very different from other predatory dinosaurs,
مختلف كثيرًا عن غيره من الديناصورات المفترسة،
very different from the T. rex.
مختلف قطعيًا عن التيرانوصور
But the really interesting information came from the rest of the skeleton.
ولكن المعلومة المثيرة للاهتمام حقًا جاءت من بقية الهيكل العظمي.
We had long spines,
كان لدينا عمود فقري طويل،
the spines forming the big sail.
العمود الفقري يُشكل شراعًا كبيرًا.
We had leg bones, we had skull bones,
كان لدينا عظام الساق وعظام الجمجمة،
we had paddle-shaped feet, wide feet --
وكان لدينا قدمان واسعتان على شكل مجداف
again, very unusual, no other dinosaur has feet like this --
مرة أخرى، ومن غير العادة أن يكون لديناصور أقدام كهذه
and we think they may have been used to walk on soft sediment,
نعقد أنه ربما استخدمت للمشي على الرواسب اللينة
or maybe for paddling in the water.
أو لعلها مجاديف في الماء
We also looked at the fine microstructure of the bone,
وأيضًا ألقينا نظرة على البنية المجهرية الدقيقة للعظم،
the inside structure of Spinosaurus bones,
للهيكل الداخلي لعظام السبينوصور،
and it turns out that they're very dense and compact.
وتبين لنا أنها غليظة جدا وصغيرة الحجم
Again, this is something we see in animals that spend a lot of time in the water,
مرة أخرى، هذا شيء نراه في الحيوانات التي تقضي الكثير من الوقت في الماء،
it's useful for buoyancy control in the water.
وذلك مفيد في التحكم في الطفو على الماء.
We C.T.-scanned all of our bones and built a digital Spinosaurus skeleton.
في المركز قمنا بمسح ضوئي لجميع العظام وبنينا على ذلك هيكل رقمي للسبينوصور
And when we looked at the digital skeleton,
وعندما ألقينا نظرة على الهيكل الرقمي
we realized that yes, this was a dinosaur unlike any other.
أدركنا أنه بالفعل هذا الديناصور لا مثيل له
It's bigger than a T. rex,
إنه أضخم من التيرانوصور،
and yes, the head has "fish-eating" written all over it,
وأجل، فقد كان آكلا للسمك وهذا ظاهر عليه بوضوح
but really the entire skeleton has "water-loving" written all over it --
ولكن في الحقيقة كل الهيكل العظمي يبدوا عليه أنه أليف للماء
dense bone, paddle-like feet, and the hind limbs are reduced in size,
العظام الغليظة والقدمان مثل المجداف، والأطراف الخلفية صغيرة الحجم،
and again, this is something we see in animals
مجددًا، هذا شيء نراه في الحيوانات
that spend a substantial amount of time in the water.
التي تقضى قدرًا كبيرًا من الوقت في الماء.
So, as we fleshed out our Spinosaurus --
لذا، وفي خضم بلورة السبينوصور
I'm looking at muscle attachments and wrapping our dinosaur in skin --
كنت أبحث عن عضلة مٌرفقة وكَسْوة جلدية للديناصور
we realize that we're dealing with a river monster,
أدركنا أننا نتعامل مع وحش نهري
a predatory dinosaur, bigger than T. rex,
ديناصور مفترس، أضخم من التيرانوصور،
the ruler of this ancient river of giants,
حاكم عمالقة هذ النهر القديم،
feeding on the many aquatic animals I showed you earlier on.
يتغذى على العديد من الحيوانات المائية كما أوضحت لكم سابقًا.
So that's really what makes this an incredible discovery.
وكان هذا بالفعل ما جعله اكتشافا مذهل.
It's a dinosaur like no other.
فهو ديناصور لا مثيل له.
And some people told me, "Wow, this is a once-in-a-lifetime discovery.
وأخبرني بعض الناس، "مبهر، هذا اكتشاف العمر.
There are not many things left to discover in the world."
ما تبقى في العالم إلا القليل ليتم اكتشافه."
Well, I think nothing could be further from the truth.
حسنا، أعتقد أن لا شيء يمكن أن يكون أبعد عن الحقيقة.
I think the Sahara's still full of treasures,
أعتقد أن الصحراء ما زلت ممتلئة بالكنوز،
and when people tell me there are no places left to explore,
عندما يخبرني الناس أنه لا يوجد مكان لاكتشافه،
I like to quote a famous dinosaur hunter, Roy Chapman Andrews,
أود أن أقتبس لصياد الديناصورات الشهير، "روي تشابمان اندروز"،
and he said, "Always, there has been an adventure just around the corner --
قال: "هناك دائمًا مغامرة في ناصية الشارع
and the world is still full of corners."
والعالم مازال مليئا بالشوارع."
That was true many decades ago
كان ذلك صحيحًا قبل عدة عقود
when Roy Chapman Andrews wrote these lines.
عندما كتب روي تشابمان اندروز تلك السطور
And it is still true today.
ولا يزال صحيحا ليومنا هذا.
Thank you.
شكرًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)